---HTML SYLLABUS---
CSE326
:
INTERNET PROGRAMMING LABORATORY
Course Outcomes:
CO1 :: 
understand the structure and semantics of HTML5 to create well-formed web pages.
CO2 :: 
apply HTML elements to build pages with links, images, and embedded media to design 
user-friendly and content-rich websites.
CO3 :: 
create responsive layouts using CSS, including Flexbox and Grid.
Unit I
Fundamentals of HTML
 : 
Introduction to Web Technologies and HTML, Structure of an HTML 
Document, Root and Metadata Elements, Basic Tags: Headings, Paragraphs, Line Breaks, Horizontal 
Rules, Text Formatting in HTML, strong, em, mark, small, abbr, cite, dfn, Quotations and Comments, 
Types of HTML Tags: Paired and Unpaired, Block-level vs Inline elements
Unit II
Expanding HTML Knowledge
 : 
Working with Lists: Ordered, Unordered, Definition Lists, Hyperlinks, 
Inserting Images, Embedding Media, HTML Favicon, HTML Div, HTML Text Formatting, Working With 
Tables-Colspan and Rowspan, Working with Forms- action attribute, get and post methods, Form 
Elements and Controls Like Text Inputs,, TextArea, Buttons, CheckBoxes, Dropdown Boxes, Radio 
Buttons,, Select and File Select
Unit III
Introduction to Cascading Style Sheets
 : 
CSS rules like link and style, CSS properties like text 
controlling and text formatting, CSS selectors like type, id, class, Introduction To CSS and types of 
CSS, Inline CSS, Internal CSS, External CSS, CSS Box Model- Padding, Margin, Border, Div and Span 
Tag in CSS, Working with background Images, Fonts & Typography: font-family, font-size, line-
height, font-weight, text-align, applying css on tables, creating hoverable tables, applying css on all 
controls of forms
Unit IV
JavaScript Application Development
 : 
Incorporating JavaScript in the HEAD and BODY element, 
Using an External JavaScript file, Using variables and operators, Using control statements such as 
if...else, switch, break and continue, Using looping statements such as while, do...while, for, Using 
Popup boxes such as Alert, Confirm, and Prompt, Working with JavaScript Objects,Properties and 
Methods, Variables: var, let, const
Unit V
JavaScript Functions,Events and Validation
 : 
Working with Functions-Using function arguments 
and return statement, Working with JavaScript Events like Form Based, Keyboard Based and Mouse 
Based, JavaScript Form Validation
Unit VI
Javascript DOM
 : 
DOM introduction, DOM methods, DOM document, DOM elements, DOM HTML, 
DOM CSS, DOM Events
Text
 Books
:
1
. 
MASTERING HTML, CSS & JAVA SCRIPT WEB PUBLISHING by LAURA LE MAY, RAFE 
COLBURN, JENNIFER KYRNIN, BPB PUBLICATIONS  
Reference
s
:
1
. 
HTML 5 BLACK BOOK by DT EDITORIAL SERVICES, DREAMTECH PRESS 
CO4 :: 
construct and  style tables , implementing forms controls and apply css to enhance the 
layout  and functionality of web forms
CO5 :: 
apply JavaScript to add logic, control flow, and interactivity to web pages
CO6 :: 
manipulate the DOM and handle events for dynamic content updates and validation.
Through this course students should be able to
L:
0
   
T:
0
   
P:
3
    
Credits
:
2
  
Session  20
25
-
26
                  Page:
1
/
2

Session  20
25
-
26
                  Page:
2
/
2

---JAVA SYLLABUS---
CSE380
:
PROGRAMMING IN JAVA
Course Outcomes:
CO1 :: 
evaluate the Java platform's ability to achieve platform independence and differentiate 
between various Java platforms and their uses.
CO2 :: 
apply string manipulation, data formatting, and conditionals effectively in Java programs.
CO3 :: 
describe objects and classes, and demonstrate the use of methods, encapsulation, 
inheritance, and polymorphism in Java.
CO4 :: 
analyze access levels, method overriding, and abstract classes to design robust Java 
applications
CO5 :: 
create modular Java programs by implementing interfaces, utilizing lambda expressions, 
and effectively handling exceptions and assertions.
CO6 :: 
demonstrate I/O fundamentals and utilize collections and generics to manage data 
efficiently in Java applications.
Through this course students should be able to
Java Platform Overview
ò
Defining how the Java language achieves platform independence,Differentiating between the Java 
ME, Java SE, and Java EE Platforms, Evaluating Java libraries,middle-ware, and database options, 
Defining how the Java language continues to evolve
What Is a Java Program?
ò
Introduction to Computer Programs, Key Features of the Java Language, The Java Technology and 
Development Environment, Running/testing a Java program
Creating a Java Main Class
ò
Java Classes, The main Method
Data In the Cart
ò
Introducing variables, Working with Strings, Working with numbers,Manipulating numeric data
Managing Multiple Items
ò
Working with Conditions, Working with a List of Items, Processing alist of items
Manipulating and Formatting the Data in Your Program
ò
Using the String Class, Using theStringBuilder Class, More about primitive data types, The remaining 
numeric operators, Promotingand casting variables
More on Conditionals
ò
Relational and conditional operators, Ways to use if/else constructs, Using Switch Statements.
More on Arrays and Loops
ò
Working with Dates, Parsing the args Array, 2D  Arrays, Alternate Looping Constructs, Nesting Loops, 
The ArrayList class.
Describing Objects and Classes
ò
Working with objects and classes, Defining fields and methods, Declaring, Instantiating, and 
Initializing Objects, Working with Object References, Doing more with Arrays.
Creating and Using Methods
ò
Using methods, Method arguments and return values, Static methods and variables, How Arguments 
are Passed to a Method, Overloading a method.
Using Inheritance
List of Practicals / Experiments:
L:
0
   
T:
0
   
P:
4
    
Credits
:
2
  
Session  20
25
-
26
                  Page:
1
/
2

Text
 Books
:
1
. 
INTRODUCTION TO JAVA PROGRAMMING by Y. DANIEL LIANG, PEARSON 
Reference
s
:
1
. 
JAVA THE COMPLETE REFERENCE by HERBERT SCHILDT, MCGRAW, HILL & CO PUB 
2
. 
HEAD FIRST JAVA: A BRAIN-FRIENDLY GUIDE by KATHY SIERRA, O Reilly Publishing 
ò
Overview of inheritance, Working with sub-classes and super-classes, Overriding methods in the 
superclass, Introducing polymorphism, Creating and extending abstract classes, Modeling business 
problems using Java classes, Making classes immutable.
Overriding Methods, Polymorphism, and Static Classes
ò
Using access levels: private, protected, default, and public, Overriding methods, Using virtual method 
invocation, Using varargs to specify variable arguments, Using the instance of operator to compare 
object types, Using upward and downward casts, Modeling business problems using the static 
keyword, Implementing the singleton design pattern.
Abstract and Nested Classes
ò
Designing general-purpose base classes by using abstract classes, Constructing abstract Java classes 
and subclasses, Applying final keyword in Java, Distinguish between top-level and nested classes.
Using Interfaces
ò
Polymorphism in the JDK foundation classes, Using Interfaces, Using the List Interface, Introducing 
Lambda expressions.
Interfaces and Lambda Expressions
ò
Defining a Java interface, Choosing between interface, inheritance and class inheritance, Extending 
an interface, Defaulting methods, Anonymous inner classes, Defining a Lambda Expression.
Exceptions and Assertions
ò
Handling Exceptions: An overview, Propagation of exceptions, Catching and throwing exceptions, 
Handling multiple exceptions and errors, Defining the purpose of Java exceptions, Using the try and 
throw statements, Using the catch, multi-catch, and finally clauses, Autoclose resources with a try-
with-resources statement, Recognizing common exception classes and categories, Creating custom 
exceptions, Testing invariants by using assertions.
I/O Fundamentals
ò
Describing the basics of input and output in Java, Read and write data from different sources, Using 
streams to read and write files, Writing and read objects using serialization.
Collections and Generics
ò
Creating a custom generic class, Using the type inference diamond to create an object, Creating a 
collection by using generics, Implementing an ArrayList, Implementing a TreeSet, Implementing a 
HashMap, Implementing a Deque, Ordering collections.
Session  20
25
-
26
                  Page:
2
/
2

